你这时候看面筋
Now we take a look at the gluten
你看就出来了
You see the changes
越看就好看了
Seems more and more beautiful
跟花胶肚似的
It is looks like fish maw
好多网友都要喝胡辣汤嘞
Many friends want to taste the pepper spicy soup
太中了
Sure, let’s do it
哎呦 李党
What’s up, Li Dang
师父好
Hello, Master
这次给我们带来什么好菜
Which cuisine are you bringing us today?
他是我们老家的
The cuisine is from my hometown.
叫胡辣汤
Its name is pepper spicy soup
哎呀 这回太中了
Great! It is excellent!
中的很这次
Best of the best
今天早来一会提前把这个面先和好
We come here early to knead the dough today.
因为啥
Why?
他这做胡辣汤需要什么
What do we need to cook the pepper spicy soup?
面筋
We need the gluten
早上就吃完这个早餐以后
After breakfast,
开始把面先给它饧上
we knead the dough and start to let it rest
饧了以后时间越长
The longer the dough rest,
它面筋越筋道
the more chewy the gluten will be.
我们真正的河南人做胡辣汤
Pepper spicy soup cooked by authentic Henan chef.
你看正宗不正宗
Try and see how authentic it is!
咱这个面和的时候
When we knead the dough,
也是高筋粉
Is it high-gluten flour?
一是高筋特筋的
Yes, use high-gluten flour.
您看这面饧的时间越长
See, rest the dough longer
让这个面呢一定要和的稍微软一点
The dough must be made very soft.
要硬的话它不好饧
If it is hard, it takes a lot more effort to rest.
这时候开始加水给它洗一下
Then, add some water to wash it
等一下洗的面筋水呢
The water we use to wash the dough
咱们直做胡辣汤了
Will be used to make the pepper spicy soup
这就是喝胡辣汤为什么滑
That’s why the soup tastes smooth
就是从这个因起来的
This is the reason
没糟蹋啊
No wasted ingredients!
大爷您看这配料也很全
Look, Da Ye, the ingredients are plenty
花生 黄花 木耳
Peanuts, daylilies, and black fungus
粉丝
Glass noodles
还有点肉
And some meat
这什么肉啊
What kind of meat is it?
这时候洗这个面筋
Now we wash the dough to get gluten
一定要拿手这样搓着洗
We must use our hands to twist it, like this
这样它洗出来就是滑
Only in this way, we can make the soup smooth
把面筋里边的面水给洗出来
We need to wash out all the starch from the dough
洗完之后它才称为筋
What is left is pure gluten
一斤面要洗出面筋能洗出多少
How much gluten can be made from 0.5 kg dough?
洗面筋的话
Basically, the gluten
基本上能洗出来
Can be produced
也就是四两左右
About 200 g
在家自己洗
If you wash the dough by yourself,
其实挺好玩的
it is interesting
二伯也洗过面筋 素肥肠
Er Bai has washed it before. (To make) the vegetarian intestine
素排骨都得用这个
And vegetarian ribs. Both of them need it.
好
Ok
咱们先搁着泡一会
Soak it in the water for a while
咱们开始炒料
We start to sauté the ingredients
一会再洗一下
I will wash it again later
这样咱就好了
Here we go
这时候咱们把这个汤给它篦出来
Let’s filter out the starch water
留着 再洗一遍
Keep it. Wash again
再洗一遍
Wash again
啥时候把这个色给它洗的稍微发黄一点
Wash until the gluten turns yellow
他是一边边的洗这样他才透亮
The gluten becomes bright after washing many times
把这个汤给他留着
Save the starch water for him
给你搁后面
I am putting it behind you
洗面筋最少得洗三遍
The dough needs to be washed at least three times
再来一遍
One more time
大爷您可以开水了
Da Ye, you can turn on the tap now
我就只能负责开水了
I can only take charge of the tap now
现在我这身子骨也就开水了
Based on my physical conditions
河南在面食的发展上
Throughout the history of cuisine made from wheat
应该说是它是独树一帜
Henan has its unique position
这时候就开始发黄了
Now, the gluten turns yellow
对
Right
大家可以看一下他的面
We can take a look at the gluten now
出来的就是精华
What is left is the essence.
我们就放这开始炒料
We put it here and start to saute the ingredients
这配料还真挺全乎
We have many different ingredients
牛肉胡辣汤
Beef pepper spicy soup
牛肉
Beef
咱们泡好的花生米
Pre-soaked peanuts
黄花菜
Daylilies
加上咱们的木耳
And the black fungus
海带
kelp
香菇丝
shiitake mushroom shreds
平菇
oyster mushroom
加点粉条
And some glass noodles
还有小料 葱姜
And some spices: green onions, ginger.
这边是五香粉
This is five spice powder
加上这个辣椒面
Chili powder
还有白胡椒
And white pepper
这时候咱们锅中先加点油
Now we add some oil to the pan
先下肉
Add the meat first
这个不用腌是吧
We don't need to marinate the beef, right?
不用腌
Nope
把牛肉的香味直接炒到里面
Sauté the beef to release its aroma
小点火
Turn down the heat
还下什么呀
What else do you need?
葱姜蒜末得放一点
Add some minced green onion, ginger and garlic
这时候咱们加点酱油
Now let's add some soy sauce
它这个酱油一定搁锅里边给它砸一下
The soy sauce needs some boiling time in the pan
来一点黄酒
Add some huangjiu rice wine
去去腥
to remove gamey taste
好
Ok
家里的火是大火
Use high heat if you are cooking at home
香味儿出来了
The aroma starts to flow
炝一下肉咱们可以加水了
We can add water after briefly sautéing the meat
准备好了
Here comes the water
加入清水加清水
Add some pure water
咱们就是做一汤盆
We are only making one pot of soup
咱自己家喝有时候一汤盆就够了
One pot of soup is usually enough for our family
看看咱们家里人多少
It depends on the number of people in our family
根据咱自己喝多少
We cook however much we want to drink
所以说咱们自己做多少
这时候咱们可以把这料加里面
Now we can put the ingredients in
火开大点
Turn up the heat
泡得的生花生
Presoaked raw peanuts
这样的话他等会吃的脆
They will taste crispy after soaking
然后这时候咱们把泡好的木耳黄花
Then we put presoaked black fungus and daylilies
加入里面
into the pan
海带丝
shredded kelp
多搁点汤人多
Add more water. We have many people here
粉条
glass noodles
粉条海带
glass noodles and kelp
平蘑香菇 花生米
shiitake mushroom, oyster mushroom and peanut
黄花
Daylilies
木耳
Black fungus
都放进去了
All in
要是我们老家放我们老家那种
In Henan, we will add our special
豆皮丝也行
shredded tofu skin
加点豆皮丝
add some shredded tofu skin
这个也不是不拘一格 是吧
There is no limitation, right?
不拘一格
No limitation
有时候有什么蔬菜
Sometimes it depends on what vegetables you have
你想放点什么
what you want to add
但是海带不能少
But kelp is necessary
因为海带提鲜
because kelp can bring savory taste
海带跟面筋花生这三样
Kelp，gluten and peanuts
是绝对必须要放
are necessary
海带花生还有面筋
Kelp, peanuts and gluten
这时候咱们调一下味
Now we season the soup
那么首先放胡椒粉
First we add some pepper powder
像咱们做基本上胡椒粉
The amount of pepper powder we use,
根据咱们自己
depends on our own
就是说口味
taste
因为原来最早河南做胡辣汤
In the original recipe of pepper spicy soup in Henan,
胡椒粉要多
there is a lot of pepper powder
胡辣汤它没有那么辣
(The original) pepper spicy soup is actually not that spicy
现在随着生活质量在提高
With the improvement of life quality
很多人很多都爱吃一些
A lot of people begin to enjoy some (spicy food)
早上出汗的时候怎么办
(They want to) sweat in the morning. What would you do if you want sweat?
那就得辣
You need to eat spicy food
这胡辣汤胡是怎么讲
Why do we call the soup "pepper spicy soup"？
胡就是胡椒粉
Pepper-- we add pepper powder
咱们再加点辣椒面
Now we add some chili powder
这是焙好的 熟的(辣椒面)
It is baked, cooked (chili powder)
而且这个辣椒在锅里边干炒
Bake the chilies dry (without oil) in a pan,
炒完以后给它磨成粉
then grind them into powder
这样的话香啊
This way, they smell good
大家注意啊
Notice here,
这就是提前焙好的辣椒面
this is the chili powder made from baked chili
拿锅干焙
Baked dry in the pan
焙完以后再给它打碎
then grinded
为什么叫胡辣啊
Why is called “pepper spicy”?
胡椒粉的胡
“pepper” as in “pepper powder”
辣椒面的辣是吧
“spicy” as in “chili powder"
再加一点点五香粉
then add some five-spice powder
但五香粉一定要少加
But only a small pinch of five-spice powder
加多了他有香料的那种味道
Too much (five-spice powder) will overshadow other aroma.
太浓它就不好吃了
Too dense spice taste wouldn’t taste as good
而且他吃到嗓子
Also, if you belch,
就是一打嗝 还有那个味
the smell comes along.
所以说一定要少放
So only a small pinch is enough
大爷您瞧见没有
You see, Da Ye,
味道还是挺纯正的
it should taste quite authentic,
从它的配料来看
based on its ingredients
一定要少放
Add only a small pinch (of five-spice powder)
有一点那个五香的那种味道
Just enough to bring the taste of the five spices
所以我们老饭骨我们请人做菜
Whenever State Banquet Master Chef invites someone to cook
一定要找什么
we always find those
一是专业厨师
professional chefs
再有一个是纯正的本地人
and genuine locals.
本土文化的佼佼者
Local culture gurus
而且都是地方风味的一些代表
Representative of the local tastes
这时候咱们加点盐
Now we add some salt
怎么都得两勺盐
At least two spoons (of salt)
开锅咱们加一点点老抽
When the soup starts to boil, we add a little bit of dark soy sauce
色彩稍微淡了一点
The color is a bit too light
加一点点老抽
Add a bit of dark soy sauce
这时候咱们开始下面筋
Now we add wheat gluten
撕这个面筋的时候
When tearing them into pieces,
一定要给他揪着点
make sure to stretch them thinner.
你不揪等会太长了
If you do not stretch it thin enough, it will end up too long
跟揪片似的 对
Just like tearing dough slices
揪出来片 它撇出来的大 滑
Gluten slices made by hand will end up bigger in size and smooth in texture
所以你看这种吃法啊
This way of cooking wheat gluten
还是挺新颖的
is quite innovative
这个面筋一定给它抻开了
Make sure to stretch the wheat gluten fully extended
它就是比较亮
It will appear very bright
还有弹性
and taste chewy
您看 面筋洗到什么程度
To what extent have we washed the dough?
你这样看 它出花这种感觉
Take a look here. The gluten piece appears like flower.
他不像咱们那种窟窿眼的面筋
It is not the same as the commercial wheat gluten full of holes.
但它这个面筋等一会煮出来一样有眼
But this wheat gluten will have some holes after cook as well.
好
Great
这时候我把刚才洗的面汤
Now I will use the starch water we washed out from the dough
这回我明白了
Now I see.
就是勾芡 淀粉
Use the starch water as slurry. Add slurry with it.
对
Right
这时候面粉勾芡之后
Adding slurry with wheat starch
跟生粉勾出来就是不一样
is different from adding slurry with cornstarch.
滑呀这个 对
This is very smooth and silky
二伯说的真是特别对
Er Bai made the point!
一是滑
It is smooth and silky.
等一下咱们胡辣汤
Later, for our pepper spicy soup,
还有一个最大的感觉就是说
another key is
不能用铁勺
do not use iron spoons
盛的时候用木勺盛
Only serve with wood spoons
这样的话容易给它澥
Otherwise it will become thin.
等一会咱盛汤的时候用木勺
When we serve the soup we will use wood spoons
没糟蹋呀
Didn't waste anything
对
Yes
物尽其用
Made the best of every ingredients
慢慢就稠了
(The soup) thickens slowly.
它比淀粉勾出来亮 匀 是吧
It is brighter and more even than slurry from cornstarch, right?
用您的话说呢
To paraphrase your words,
稳 柔
smooth and soft
差不多了
Almost done.
开锅的时候把这个沫稍微的撇一点
When the soup boils, remove the floating scum.
把沫撇出来
Remove the floating scum
其实咱们这样开着锅它不影响
In fact, it is OK to boil the soup like this
它不像咱们做其他汤
This is not like making other soups
比如说咱们芡一勾完
Once we finished adding slurry,
那必须得出锅了
we need to remove it from heat immediately.
它这个没事 可以多熬一会
This (pepper spicy soup) is fine. We can boil it longer.
因为他放了刚才有花生米啊
Because we added raw peanuts,
是吧
right?
有海带
And kelp
他这样煮一会
We cook for a while
他禁煮
They can hold longer boiling.
你这时候看这个面筋
Now check the wheat gluten
你看就出来了
You understand now
越看就好看了
It is more beautiful over time.
越看越好看
Look better and better!
跟那花胶肚似的
Just like fish maw.
面筋发亮
The gluten is bright,
浮起
floating on the surface.
这面筋煮的就跟一朵朵花似的
The cooked gluten pieces looks like flowers
来吧
Now it's done
这时候咱们放香油
Add sesame oil now
河南的正宗的胡辣汤 就中了
Authentic Henan pepper spicy soup, finished!
香菜
Some cilantro
怎么样大爷说说感受
How do you like it, Da Ye? Share some thoughts?
我看您光顾着喝了
You are so focused on eating,
话都出不来了
that you forgot to talk
不是 我得品一品这味儿啊
No, I just need to savor it carefully
我这个照相摄像我手都累了
I am very tired holding this camera
是不是
Right?
首先胡椒粉的味十足
Firstly, it is full of pepper taste.
辣味儿适度
Mildly spicy.
大爷喝了两口汗下来了
Da Ye sweats after drinking just a little (soup)
咸 香 鲜十足
Salty, savory, full of umami taste
确实代表了我们中原大地的
Indeed, it represents the food culture
饮食文化的一部分
of the central Chinese plains
这面筋好
The wheat gluten is great
这一次二伯没皱眉头
Er Bai did not frown this time
喝美了
He likes it
你们要不喝这个
If you do not drink the soup,
后悔吧
you will regret it.
你后悔一辈子
You will regret it forever.